<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-12T14:23:32+00:00</updated><id>https://www.constantine-cooke.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Postdoctoral research associate characterising heterogeneity in IBD using longitudinal biomarker profiles. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">World IBD Day: Reflecting on being both an IBD patient and researcher</title><link href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2025/World-IBD/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="World IBD Day: Reflecting on being both an IBD patient and researcher"/><published>2025-05-19T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-19T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2025/World-IBD</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2025/World-IBD/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/Lees-group-800.webp-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/Lees-group-800.webp-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/Lees-group-800.webp-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Lees-group-800.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p><br/></p> <p>This World IBD Day, I am reflecting on being both a person living with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) and a researcher aiming to improve our understanding of these conditions. Around my 18th birthday, I began experiencing symptoms of ulcerative colitis, which alongside Crohn’s disease make up the two main forms of IBD. I began needing to urgently and frequently go to the toilet and would pass blood. Like approximately 10% of people with IBD, I have a relative who also lives with IBD. In my case, my dad had already been diagnosed with ulcerative colitis which meant I quickly recognised the symptoms. Whilst it is understood that IBD has a genetic component, genetics only partially explains why someone develops the disease. The current leading hypothesis is IBD is an immune response to unknown environmental triggers in genetically susceptible individuals.</p> <p>By the time I started my university studies, I was taking a medication called mesazaline, which is a colonic anti-inflammatory, and azathiopurine, an immunosuppressant. Unfortunately, this combination failed to control my disease despite reducing my neutorphils (white blood cells which fight infections) to a very low level. This was then followed by my first biologic treatment. These are live antibodies which disrupt inflammatory processes by intercepting messages sent by the body. Initially, I was prescribed golimumab which involved regular injections in the skin at home. Later I would undergo infliximab and then vedolizumab infusions at my hospital. Unfortunately, none of these medications consistently controlled my disease. Only corticosteroids were effective, however these drugs are only able to induce remission – and cannot maintain it. Steroids are also associated with severe side effects including reducing bone density, rapid weight gain (particularly around the face), and mental health problems.</p> <p>By the third year of being a student, I was drained. I spent most of my time in bed or on the toilet, and I needed to pause my studies. I had an appointment with my gastroenterologist, where she recommended I had a colectomy with ileostomy. This involved the removal of my large intestine with the end of my small intestine being routed through my abdomen. A stoma bag would then be attached to collect my waste.</p> <p>Whilst initially a terrifying prospect, the months between the initial referral to a surgeon and the operation allowed me to come to terms with having a colectomy. Being able to reclaim my life, continue my studies, and do the things I enjoyed doing (such as swimming) greatly outweighed any self-image or stoma bag malfunction fears I had. I was incredible grateful for the freedom this appliance gave me.</p> <style type="text/css">.sidebar{height:100%;width:350px;float:left;top:10;padding-right:20px}.sidebar div{padding-right:20px;display:block;float:right}</style> <div class="sidebar"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/Stoma-800.webp-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/Stoma-800.webp-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/Stoma-800.webp-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Stoma-800.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <br/> <p class="text-red-400"> Me with an ileostomy bag </p> </div> <p>Thankfully, my operation was a success, and I was able to continue my degree and take up physical activities once more. However, shortly before my final exams began, I once again experienced ulcerative colitis symptoms. My rectum, one of the final segments of the GI tract, had been left intact by the previous operation. However, this segment now needed to be removed.</p> <p>This operation did not go smoothly, and I developed sepsis from a haematoma (where blood collects outside of blood vessels). This required readmission, a heavy dose of antibiotics and a trip to the radiology department for the insertion of a drain. Fortunately, I recovered fast enough to be able to sit my exams in the resit period, albeit with the drain still in.</p> <p>My Masters degree in Biological Data Science was much less turbulent. Afterwards, I knew I wanted to stay in academia and do a PhD. However, when I searched for research projects applicable to my skillset, nothing particularly appealed to me. Given my history, I searched for IBD projects out of interest, expecting all of the projects would be aimed at clinicians or biologists. However, I came across a project proposed by Dr Catalina Vallejos and Professor Charlie Lees which greatly interested me, was highly relevant to my skillset, and became my PhD. In many ways, this is still the theme of my work to this day.</p> <p>Whilst there are people living with IBD who have similar stories to me, there are lots of other people with very different stories. Some have had a much worse experience than me, whilst there are others who go on to never experience symptoms again after their diagnosis. It is this variety, and our inability to accurately predict how a patient’s disease will progress, which drives a substantial portion of modern IBD research. My research in the Lees group involves using hospital test data over time, collected via regular care delivery, to identify subgroups of patients. Typically, when a test used to monitor IBD is requested, only the prior test result or short-term trends are considered. My work incorporates test results over a longer time frame to identify subgroups of patients with different disease activities. We believe that we can then use these data to better predict which patients will experience a poor disease course and would benefit from enhanced care.</p> <p>During my PhD, I underwent my (hopefully) final operation where an internal pouch was formed using the end of my small intestine – negating the need to use stoma bags. My day-to-day life is now largely unaffected by IBD. I take loperamide, a medication with very few side effects, and I need to use the toilet slightly more often than most people. My only remaining symptom is fatigue, (which I have been known to attempt to manage via caffeinated beverages).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="ibd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are There Groups of Crohn’s Disease Patients with Similar Faecal Calprotectin Patterns Over Time?</title><link href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2023/lcmm-cgh/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are There Groups of Crohn’s Disease Patients with Similar Faecal Calprotectin Patterns Over Time?"/><published>2023-04-06T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-06T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2023/lcmm-cgh</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2023/lcmm-cgh/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/fcal-800.webp-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/fcal-800.webp-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/fcal-800.webp-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/fcal-800.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p><br/> People with Crohn’s disease are likely to be very familiar with faecal calprotectin kits; these tests use a stool sample to determine the amount of gastrointestinal inflammation a person has. Gastroenterologists often use the results from these kits to assist with determining how active a person’s Crohn’s disease is without needing that person needing to undergo a colonoscopy.</p> <p>We know it is crucial faecal calprotectin is kept low early after diagnosis to improve the likelihood a Crohn’s disease patient is going to have a good outcome. My colleagues at the University of Edinburgh and NHS Lothian have previously shown having a calprotectin below \(250 \; (\mu g/g)\) a year after diagnosis reduces the likelihood of the disease worsening and patients being hospitalised or requiring surgery <a class="citation" href="#Plevris2021">(Plevris et al., 2021)</a>. However, this previous work did not consider calprotectin as a measurement which changes continuously over time and instead ony considered two measurements for each person measured a year apart.</p> <p>We believed that across people with Crohn’s disease, there were likely common patterns of faecal calprotectin over time. To the best of our knowledge, no previous research had attempted to determine if we can group people with Crohn’s disease with other Crohn’s disease patients with similar calprotectin over time. Recently, colleagues and I have attempted to determine how many groups with their own shared calprotectin patterns can be reliably found, what these patterns look like, and if being in one of these groups are potentially affected by the data known at diagnosis <a class="citation" href="#Constantine_Cooke_2023">(Constantine-Cooke et al., 2023)</a>.</p> <p>For our study, we considered the calprotectin of 356 people with Crohn’s disease and followed them from diagnosis for five years. We have used highly flexible statistical models, known as latent class mixed models with natural cubic splines, to determine the number of groups with distinct calprotectin patterns and their appearance.</p> <p>We found four distinct groups which are presented below and largely reflect what is seen by gastroenterologists in clinics. Three of the groups can be broadly described as having overall decreasing calprotectin over time with the fourth group (cluster 2) having consistently high calprotectin. It is highly likely there are patients in this latter group who would have benefitted from receiving more advanced therapies sooner and also patients who would have always had aggressive disease regardless of the treatment they received. We are interested in determining which patients this is the case for in the future. <br/><br/></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/traj-800.webp-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/traj-800.webp-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/traj-800.webp-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/traj-800.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p><br/></p> <p class="text-red-400"> The four distinct calprotectin profiles we found. The gray lines are the calprotectin measurements for each subject deemed to have a similar profile to the red curve. </p> <p>Of the data which are typically available at diagnosis, only smoking status and the presence of upper gastrointestinal inflammation were found to be significantly associated with which group a patient was assigned to. Smokers were more likely to be assigned to class 1 or 2 whilst people with upper gastrointestinal disease were less likely to be assigned to class 1. Whilst smokers being assigned to class 2 makes sense as smoking is highly associated with worse disease outcomes in Crohn’s disease, we do not fully understand the association we found between smoking and class 1. However, this may be due to smokers in class 1 giving up smoking after being diagnosed. Unfortunately, we do not have data for whether patients gave up smoking, and this is simply a theory.</p> <p>We found early biologic treatment being very highly associated with class membership with those in class 2 being less likely to receive early biologic treatment than the other groups. However, We were unable to accurately predict class membership using all variables available at diagnosis and data science techniques (random forest and multinomial logistic regression).</p> <p>Overall, we have shown latent class mixed models are an excellent tool for finding subgroups of people with Crohn’s disease with shared calprotectin profiles and determining these profiles in a data-driven manner (rather than asking patients which diagram shown to them best described their disease).</p> <p>We are currently working on expanding this work to include all ulcerative colitis and Crohn’s disease patients treated by the Edinburgh IBD Unit and model both CRP and calprotectin.</p> <p>Our long-term goal is to develop a tool which will predict a patient’s risk of surgery, hospitalisation, or worsening disease based on symptoms, calprotectin, and other measures which will then update as additional measurements are taken. This could then help clinicians when making decisions such as which treatment plan to place a patient on and how closely a patient should be monitored.</p> <hr/> <p><br/></p> <p class="text-2xl">References</p> <p><br/></p> <ol class="bibliography"><li> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-2 abbr"></div> <div id="Plevris2021" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">Normalization of fecal calprotectin within 12 months of diagnosis is associated with reduced risk of disease progression in patients with Crohn’s disease</div> <div class="author">Nikolas Plevris,&nbsp;James Fulforth,&nbsp;Mathew Lyons,&nbsp;Spyros I. Siakavellas,&nbsp;Philip W. Jenkinson,&nbsp;Cher S. Chuah,&nbsp;Laura Lucaciu,&nbsp;Rebecca J. Pattenden,&nbsp;Ian D. Arnott,&nbsp;Gareth-Rhys Jones,&nbsp;and <a href="https://charlielees.com">Charlie W. Lees</a> </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>Clinical Gastroenterology and Hepatology</em> Sep 2021 </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div></li> <li> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-2 abbr"></div> <div id="Constantine_Cooke_2023" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">Longitudinal Fecal Calprotectin Profiles Characterize Disease Course Heterogeneity in Crohn’s Disease</div> <div class="author"> <em>Nathan Constantine-Cooke</em>,&nbsp;Karla Monterrubio-Gómez,&nbsp;Nikolas Plevris,&nbsp;Lauranne A.A.P. Derikx,&nbsp;Beatriz Gros,&nbsp;Gareth-Rhys Jones,&nbsp;Riccardo E. Marioni,&nbsp;<a href="https://charlielees.com">Charlie W. Lees</a>,&nbsp;and <a href="https://vallejosgroup.github.io">Catalina A. Vallejos</a> </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>Clinical Gastroenterology and Hepatology</em> Mar 2023 </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div></li></ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="calprotectin"/><category term="crohn&apos;s-disease"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[People with Crohn’s disease are likely to be very familiar with faecal calprotectin kits; these tests use a stool sample to determine the amount of gastrointestinal inflammation a person has. Gastroenterologists often use the results from these kits to assist with determining how active a person’s Crohn’s disease is without needing that person needing to undergo a colonoscopy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing datefixR</title><link href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2022/datefixr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing datefixR"/><published>2022-02-23T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-23T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2022/datefixr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2022/datefixr/"><![CDATA[<p>You are a data scientist living your best life: “<a href="https://hbr.org/2012/10/data-scientist-the-sexiest-job-of-the-21st-century">I have the sexiest job of the 21<sup>st</sup> century</a>” you mutter under your breath as you work. Then tragedy strikes. That new dataset you just received? It has date data. And not just any date data- date data which has been provided by a free-text web form. You scroll through the data, the dates are in many different formats: day of the month first, year first, - or / separators, month given as an abbreviation or in full. “This is going to be a nightmare to standardise” you think to yourself. This is decidedly <em>unsexy</em>.</p> <p>Fortunately, this is where the datefixR R package comes in. In a single function call, all of these date data can be standardised into one format. datefixR’s <a href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/datefixR/reference/fix_dates.html"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fix_dates()</code></a> function takes a dataframe (or tibble) object and the names of any columns with date data and returns a dataframe object where the selected columns have been standardised and converted to R’s built-in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Date</code> class (which follows the <a href="https://www.iso.org/iso-8601-date-and-time-format.html">ISO 8601 format</a>). If there are any dates which cannot be resolved, an error will be raised providing the date and associated ID (assumed to be the first column if not explicitly provided).</p> <p>Congratulations! You have potentially just saved yourself a whole lot of time. Now you can run the analysis you actually want to do!</p> <p>If you are interested in learning how to make the most of the datefixR, check its <a href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/datefixR/articles/datefixR.html">getting started vignette</a></p> <p>datefixR is available on <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=datefixR">CRAN</a>.</p> <p><br/></p> <h2 id="faqs">FAQs</h2> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Q:</strong> Is the US date standard (month-first) supported? <br/> <strong>A</strong> Yes! Just provide the argument <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">format = "mdy"</code>when calling <a href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/datefixR/reference/fix_dates.html"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fix_dates()</code></a></p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Q:</strong> Can I just standardise a single date? <br/> <strong>A</strong> Yes! Just use the <a href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/datefixR/reference/fix_date.html"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fix_date()</code></a> function. Please note that this might be slightly slower in a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">for</code> loop than when using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fix_dates()</code>.</p> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data-science"/><category term="Programming"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Your data wrangling saviour?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">After COVID, Academia Should Re-Evaluate its Opinion of Code</title><link href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2020/coding/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="After COVID, Academia Should Re-Evaluate its Opinion of Code"/><published>2020-06-09T19:32:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-09T19:32:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2020/coding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2020/coding/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/coding-800.webp-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/coding-800.webp-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/coding-800.webp-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/coding-800.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>As the lockdown starts to ease in the UK, reflection on the nation’s response to the COVID-19 pandemic has begun in earnest. A particular focus has been on Imperial’s epidemiological model, originally created by Neil Ferguson, which was widely credited with convincing the government to implement lockdown measures after it forecast up to half a million COVID-19 deaths in the UK if a mitigation strategy was not implemented. Criticism of the model has been levelled by the press: particularly those with an editorial stance against strict lockdown measures and a love of the word ‘draconian’ (<a href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-8294439/ROSS-CLARK-Neil-Fergusons-lockdown-predictions-dodgy.html">Daily Mail</a>, the <a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2020/05/10/chilling-truth-decision-impose-lockdown-based-crude-mathematical/">Telegraph</a>).</p> <style type="text/css">.twitter{height:100%;width:400px;float:right;padding:3px}.twitter div{display:block;float:left}</style> <div class="twitter"> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"> <a href="https://twitter.com/neil_ferguson/status/1241835454707699713?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I’m conscious that lots of people would like to see and run the pandemic simulation code we are using to model control measures against COVID-19. To explain the background - I wrote the code (thousands of lines of undocumented C) 13+ years ago to model flu pandemics...</p>&mdash; neil_ferguson (@neil_ferguson) March 22, 2020</a></blockquote> </div> <p>What does seem to be clear is the Imperial model drastically over-estimated deaths, was originally intended for influenza, and was written in poor quality code. The code, written in C, was over <a href="https://twitter.com/neil_ferguson/status/1241835454707699713">13 years old, undocumented and thousands of lines long</a>. When it was <a href="https://github.com/mrc-ide/covid-sim">made public on GitHub</a>, there was an uproar from professional software engineers. The code was labelled “horrible” and “a buggy mess” on issues created for the repository (which also lacked unit tests). Software engineers were appalled code of its quality was being used to inform the national response to COVID. Some even went as far as to <a href="https://github.com/mrc-ide/covid-sim/issues/165">call for the retraction of all papers based on the model</a>.</p> <p>There were also concerns after external researchers said they were unable to reproduce the results described by Imperial. This further undermined faith in the model and was leapt on by the press. Recently, the scientific community has concluded these differences were due to differing computing environments and the results are <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-01685-y">now deemed to be reproducible</a>. This is not likely to sway the opinion of people who read the many articles questioning if the model was reproducible. It is unlikely papers will write stories covering the model being shown to be reproducible in the same way they covered fears of the model not being reproducible.</p> <p>In addition to poor code quality reducing trust in the model, it also inevitably made editing and contributing to the code difficult. Ferguson justified using a model intended for influenza predictions for COVID-19 predictions instead due to urgency at the time for models and the time which would be required to develop a COVID-19 specific model. Whilst this this a valid point, the poor code quality surely inhibited being able to quickly adapt this model for COVID-19. Contributions from GitHub, Microsoft, and individual developers have eventually enabled the model to become specialised for COVID but this has required substantial effort and time.</p> <p>It would be easy to place the blame for the code quality squarely at the feet of Ferguson, but I think we should instead blame an academic culture which does not value code. In academia, we commonly do not see code as being anywhere near as important as the research paper the code is based on. Code in academia is commonly used simply to validate a model’s effectiveness. In many cases, code is still not made public at all. A current research interest of mine is joint models for longitudinal and time-to-event data. Despite numerous papers proposing implementations of such methods, it is possible to count on one hand the number of public packages available which implement joint models. I do not think it is surprising many academics spend little time ensuring high code quality. Documenting and refactoring code takes time and arguably receives little reward for the time required.  Why go through this process when you can be working on a new paper instead which will earn you citations? Some may argue being able to produce code that others can easily use will increase the citation count of the paper the code compliments, but not citing software is already believed to be a problem rife in academia. I believe more needs to be done to promote writing high quality code in academia. The two propositions I’ve presented below may seem naive but hopefully they at least start a discussion.</p> <p>It should become commonplace to incorporate software downloads as a measure of researcher’s output in addition to metrics based on citations. Software downloads for software stored on public repositories can be easily tracked and gives a good indicator of the impact an academic is making on the community.</p> <p>Some argue poor code quality is inherent when people who are not software engineers write code. I therefore suggest that universities should hire software engineers to work with researchers to ensure code is well written, suitably tested, and adequately documented.</p> <p>I think these approaches would at least go some way towards improving code quality in academia and result in more useful output. This would allow more methods to actually be utilised instead of simply being left in papers and supplementary material. And who knows, maybe your code would be used to influence government policy without raising vocal opposition.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data-science"/><category term="Programming"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Experience of Being a PhD Student with a Chronic Health Condition (Thus Far)</title><link href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2019/experience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Experience of Being a PhD Student with a Chronic Health Condition (Thus Far)"/><published>2019-12-29T19:26:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-29T19:26:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2019/experience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2019/experience/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog-3-header-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog-3-header-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog-3-header-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog-3-header.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>It is the Christmas holiday and, despite being very busy working on an R package for survival analysis, I have also found the time to be reflect on the first few months of my PhD.</p> <p>In particular, I have been considering my experience thus far as a PhD student with a chronic condition and how I can best balance my health and my work. I have decided to share my experience with the wider academic community but it should be taken as precisely that: my experience. There are undoubtedly people who have had very different experiences than me due to many different factors including different health condition(s), a different university, or different supervisors.</p> <p>I have ulcerative colitis, one of two inflammatory bowel diseases (IBD) which are the focus of my research (as a biomedical data scientist). Diagnosed 5 years ago, I underwent all of the non-experimental medical interventions available to me before electing to have a partial colectomy (large intestine removal) which was subsequently followed up with additional surgery to remove the rest of my large intestine and around two thirds of my rectum.</p> <style type="text/css">.sidebar{height:100%;width:350px;float:right;top:10;padding:40px}.sidebar div{padding:40px;display:block;float:left}</style> <div class="sidebar"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/0001-0119-2.gif-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/0001-0119-2.gif-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/0001-0119-2.gif-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/0001-0119-2.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <em> A digital representation of what was removed from me, because it’s prettier than a photograph would have been. </em> </div> <p>I have still been left with a small section of diseased rectum, however, which causes fatigue, discomfort and pain. I am currently awaiting further surgery to have the rest of my rectum removed, which will hopefully happen soon, but I need to balance my PhD work and health in the meantime.</p> <p>I greatly enjoy working on my PhD, but I have to be smart with how I work as the energy and focus I have will fluctuate considerably between days. PhDs are generally much more flexible than undergraduate degrees which has proven to be a great boon. I can typically choose to read literature when my concentration levels are good and I need to make sure that I fully understand what I am reading, but I can typically choose to work on coding or other tasks when my focus is much lower. I also find it very important to continue to keep busy by taking on work rather than rest for a particularly long period of time as I very quickly find myself shutting down which then makes it almost impossible to return to work again. Determination has become an increasingly precious character trait which I heavily rely on to get me through my PhD, but I do regularly have to assess the workload I have taken on and accept that it is simply not possible for me to work on as many projects as I would wish to at the moment without compromising all of the projects collectively or my health.</p> <p>I have been open with my supervisors about my health situation and my experience from doing so has been overwhelmingly positive. Both of my supervisors, Dr Catalina Vallejos and Dr Charlie Lees, have been incredible in their support of me and have always been very understanding: working with me to find the best ways of working around my health problems. This has included supporting flexible working arrangements for me for when my energy levels are particularly bad. I also reached out to the administrative officers for my PhD programme, Susan Mitchell &amp; Kate Hardman, both of whom have also been a great help and have offered advice with how to manage my course: such as postponing any taught courses until after my surgery.</p> <p>Managing a social life has become a delicate balancing act. I am fortunate to be studying at the Institute of Genetics and Molecular Medicine where there is a lively community of lovely PhD students who often invite me to social events. Unfortunately, I frequently find myself having to pass on such events as the additional fatigue resulting from going on a night out will often still be felt weeks later.</p> <p>Unfortunately, my two preferred methods of self-care, exercise and reading novels, are currently unavailable to me. The former I no longer have the necessary energy for, and the latter I no longer have the focus for (or when I have it, I need it for reading academic literature). I really need to find alternatives until I have my surgery. My third hobby, creating CGI art, helps me to switch off but involves me sitting at a computer which, as a data scientist, I already spend most of my day doing. I think I will spend at least some of 2020 trying out new ways to switch off from work and look after myself!</p> <p>And that is the end of this post! This blog is intended to be a research blog and most of my posts will be updates on my research instead of my personal life, but please feel free to follow me on Twitter for updates on any future blog posts or occasional updates on my PhD journey!</p> <div class="jekyll-twitter-plugin"><a class="twitter-timeline" data-width="500" data-tweet-limit="3" href="https://twitter.com/IBDNathan?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">Tweets by IBDNathan</a> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="student-life"/><category term="IBD"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Exciting IBD Research is Taking Place in the UK?</title><link href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2019/what-exciting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Exciting IBD Research is Taking Place in the UK?"/><published>2019-12-10T12:21:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-10T12:21:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2019/what-exciting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2019/what-exciting/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/bsg-800.webp-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/bsg-800.webp-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/bsg-800.webp-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/bsg-800.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>I know in my last blog post I said I would be talking about previous attempts to predict IBD flares in published research but plans change! On the 11th November, I attended the <a href="https://www.bsg.org.uk">British Society of Gastroenterology’s</a> IBD principal investigators meeting in London where the leads on some of the most exciting IBD studies in the UK spoke about their research (or prospective research). It was truly brilliant to meet so many people enthusiastic about research in IBD. There were talks and posters on IBD studies in addition to plenty of opportunities to have discussions. For this blog post, I am going to talk about some of the studies discussed at the meeting. In the interest of word count and due to the nature of some studies, I’ve not been able to talk about every project discussed at the meeting but here are some of them!</p> <hr/> <h2 id="ibd-bioresource">IBD BioResource</h2> <p>The <a href="https://www.ibdbioresource.nihr.ac.uk/">IBD BioResource</a> is less of a study and more of a, well… resource. Having recruited over 25,000 IBD patients, the BioResource banks patient data on disease extent, prescription response and current medication. Genetic samples are also collected for sequencing which should allow genetic markers of disease, risk severity, and drug response to be found. If consent is given, the BioResource can also be used to recruit participants to studies by genotype and/or phenotype which is a brilliant utility for researchers. Our study, PREdiCCt has a close relationship with the IBD BioResource and all of our participants have the option of also joining the BioResource when they join us.</p> <h2 id="wellcome-sanger-institute">Wellcome Sanger Institute</h2> <p>Carl Anderson, of the <a href="https://www.sanger.ac.uk/">Wellcome Sanger Institute</a>, spoke briefly on some of the work his team is using the BioResource for. Carl spoke of using genetics to predict disease course: questioning if the polygenicity of IBD explains the variation in disease outcomes. Using gene expression to find new potential drug targets was also an interesting topic of discussion.</p> <h2 id="cd-treat">CD-TREAT</h2> <p>Vaios Solos, from the <a href="https://www.gla.ac.uk/">University of Glasgow</a>, detailed <a href="http://theses.gla.ac.uk/40971/">CD-TREAT</a>. Exclusive enteral nutrition (EEN), a liquid diet, is the only established dietary treatment for Crohn’s disease, but patients often struggle to follow such a diet. Once EEN is ceased, symptoms typically return. Vaios and his collaborators have created the CD-TREAT diet which attempts to mimic the effect EEN has on the gut microbiome whilst being far more tolerable for patients by consisting of ordinary food. CD-TREAT is currently aiming to recruit 60 patients who will follow the diet for 8 weeks: unless symptoms worsen during the study. Research from CD-TREAT is already <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0016508518353988?via%3Dihub">publicly available</a>.</p> <h2 id="ibd-boost">IBD-BOOST</h2> <p>Finally, <a href="https://www.kcl.ac.uk/research/ibd-boost">IBD-BOOST</a> is a UK-wide study investigating the relationship between fatigue, pain and urgency in IBD using multiple regression. This study brings together IBD symptoms and its effect on quality of life. Some participants are then recruited to IBD-BOOST OPTIMISE which is an interventional trial in which fatigue, pain and urgency attempt to be managed via a nurse-led algorithm.</p> <hr/> <p>And that is the end of my, admittedly very short, summaries of some of the most interesting IBD research taking place in the UK. Unfortunately, my time is quite limited at present, worsened significantly by poor health. Maybe at some point I will discuss being a PhD student with a chronic condition. I should probably use my next blog post to finally talk about research which has undertaken with the aim of predicting IBD flares first, but we’ll see how that works out! Regardless of what I talk about next, <a href="https://twitter.com/IBDNathan">follow me on Twitter</a> to find out what and when I next post!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Conference"/><category term="BSG"/><category term="IBD"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Alternatively titled: Why I was insane enough to travel from Edinburgh to London and back in one day.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Plan for my PhD</title><link href="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2019/my-plan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Plan for my PhD"/><published>2019-11-01T10:54:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-01T10:54:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2019/my-plan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.constantine-cooke.com/blog/2019/my-plan/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my blog, PREdiCCting IBD Outcomes, and thank you for finding this site! I am a PhD student and a biomedical data scientist based at the MRC Human Genetics Unit at the <a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk">University of Edinburgh</a>. I am going to be building statistical models which predict when a person with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) is going to have a flare. This will improve our understanding of Crohn’s disease, ulcerative colitis, and inflammatory bowel disease unclassified (IBDU).</p> <p>I have a long way to go first, however. I am incredibly fortunate to have joined an ongoing study, <a href="https://www.predicct.co.uk">PREdiCCt</a>. This meant I did not have to worry about starting a study: writing ethics proposals or considering many of the logistics involved in setting up a study. It did mean I had an awful lot of information thrown at me as soon as I started, however. PREdiCCt is a very large UK-wide study with involvement from 42 hospitals, the <a href="https://www.sanger.ac.uk">Wellcome Sanger Institute</a> (sequencing), the <a href="https://www.abdn.ac.uk">University of Aberdeen</a> (dietary expertise), and the University of Edinburgh. As such, getting my head around the complexities of PREdiCCt has not been an easy task.</p> <p>PREdiCCt is recruiting 3100 people with IBD who are in remission (1550 with Crohn’s, 1550 with colitis or IBDU). Shortly after recruitment, participants are asked to complete a questionnaire which informs us of the participant’s history, and forms the baseline: how the participant feels when they are in remission. Participants also provide stool and saliva samples which are sequenced so we can investigate genetics and metabolites. Participants are then asked to complete short monthly questionnaires which allow us to follow their progress. If a participant reports a flare, they are asked to provide another stool sample. Participants are followed across the course of two years. If you would like to find out more about PREdiCCt, please click on the About PREdiCCt tab at the top of this blog or visit the <a href="https://www.predicct.co.uk">PREdiCCt website</a>.</p> <p>Having some of the data available almost immediately has been a huge boon. I have spent most of the first couple of weeks of my PhD understanding the data, and writing scripts (I primarily use the statistical programming language R). These scripts should become more useful once I have more data available. I have also been investigating where data is currently missing to assist the brilliant Spyros Siakavellas who is currently chasing up missing data and working on improving how data gets from various sources to our central databases. I have been experimenting with replacing the missing data with predicted values using a mixture of machine learning and classical statistical techniques.</p> <p>My next goal is to conduct a review of past attempts to predict IBD flare. Ultimately, researchers stand on the shoulders of giants and it would not be wise to conduct research without knowing what work has been undertaken previously with the same goal. As an added bonus, this review will likely be included in my thesis: meaning I will already be chipping away at that daunting document! If you are interested in reading about my findings, please revisit this site in two weeks to read my next post. You can follow me on <a href="https://twitter.com/IBDNathan">Twitter</a> to be reminded when I post.</p> <p>At present, I am still awaiting the data from the monthly follow-up questionnaires. Even without this data, it is expected there will be some interesting results from the data I do have: the baseline questionnaires completed by a participant when they join the study. There are many claims and beliefs about IBD, and this data should allow us to validate or dispute these claims.</p> <p>However, the main focus of my project is building statistical models which will predict when an IBD patient will have a flare, and I should be able to create such models once I start getting the data from the monthly follow up questionnaires. I will work on making these models as accurate as possible whilst also finding which variables are most important for improving accuracy in my models. At a later date, I will get the results of the sequencing and can incorporate genetics and metabolites into my models. This should lead to an increased understanding in the role genetics plays in the progression of IBD.</p> <p>The final goal of my project is to translate my research into medical interventions in collaboration with the <a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/centre-genomic-medicine/research-groups/charlie-lees-research-group">Lees research group</a>. This is certainly my most ambitious goal, but it would be a remarkable product of my PhD studies.</p> <p>That is everything I have done thus far, and my expectations for the future of my project, in a nutshell. Of course, as always, “the best-laid plans of mice and men often go awry” and I am sure the plan for my project will change considerably due to unexpected factors. If you are interested in hearing about my research as I do it (no matter how according to plan it goes!) please do revisit this blog in two weeks (or subscribe for email alerts/ follow me on Twitter for reminders).</p> <div class="jekyll-twitter-plugin"><a class="twitter-timeline" data-width="500" data-tweet-limit="3" href="https://twitter.com/IBDNathan?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">Tweets by IBDNathan</a> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Precision"/><category term="Medicine"/><category term="PREdiCCt"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Alternatively titled: Why am I Being Given Money for the Next 3.5 Years?]]></summary></entry></feed>